Maggie Holtzberg collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Maggie Holtzberg collection 1972-2002 1983-1992
AFC 2018/013
Holtzberg, Maggie, 1955-
approximately 1100 items
sound recordings: 21 sound cassettes: analog.
graphic images: 31 slides: color; 35 mm.
graphic images: 108 photographic prints and negatives: black and white, color; various sizes.
manuscripts: 1.2 linear feet.
electronic media: 16 computer files (word perfect and .tif) on 1 floppy disk; 5.25 in.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The Maggie Holtzberg collection documents, through interviews and photographs, the occupational folklife and craft of hot metal typesetters, compositors, and printers. Holtzberg interviewed skilled craftsmen and women who experienced the disruptive technology and transition in the printing industry from mechanical typesetting, "hot metal," to computer-aided photocomposition or "cold type." She interviewed retired printers residing at the Union Printers Home in Colorado Springs, Colorado, and craft printers at Heritage Printers in Charlotte, North Carolina, among others. Interviews were conducted between 1983-1988. The collection includes the production files for Holtzberg's book, The Lost World of the Craft Printer (University of Illinois Press, 1992); correspondence with folklorists Archie Green and Judith McCulloh, and notes from meetings with Holtzberg's dissertation advisors at the University of Pennsylvania -- Henry Glassie, Ray Birdwhistell, and with Ken Goldstein, whom she interviewed about his experience in the printing industry. The collection also includes two journals written while Maggie Holtzberg was a student from 1972-1973 at the Trailside Country School, based in Killington, Vermont. The Trailside Country School was a traveling high school run by Michael Cohen and Diana Cohen that taught cultural documentation. The notebooks include diary entries, song lyrics, music transcription, and ephemera from locations throughout the United States where the students traveled. Photographs include the 46 illustrations for Holtzberg's book, 31 slides, plus snapshots from Holtzberg's fieldwork with printers and a few from the Trailside Country School. One of the interviews with printers was conducted by folklorist Jan Rosenberg.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Goldstein, Kenneth S., 1927-1995--Interviews.; Green, Archie--Correspondence.; Holtzberg, Maggie, 1955-; Holtzberg, Maggie, 1955-; McCulloh, Judith, 1935-2014--Correspondence.; Rosenberg, Jan, 1955-; Schlesinger, Carl.
Organizations
Trailside Country School.; Union Printers Home.
Subjects
High school students--United States--Diaries.; Printers--United States--Folklore.; Printers--United States--Interviews.; Printing industry--Employees--Effect of technological innovations on.; Printing industry--Social aspects--United States.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Diaries.; Field notes.; Interviews (Sound recordings); Manuscripts for publication.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Transcripts.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: 1: Interviews; 2: Manuscripts, correspondence, and production files.
Series 1: The Interviews series consists of a few folders at the series level and 19 subseries arranged alphabetically. The "Union Printers Home" subseries is divided into eight further subseries, arranged in their original chronological order. The records for the "Interviews" series were originally organized in roughly chronological order, and stored together in a three ring binder, except for the records in the "Union Printers Home" subseries. Those papers were originally organized in loose folders. The order of items within all folders have been retained.
Series 2: The Manuscripts, correspondence, and production files series consists of folders and two subseries, "The Lost World of the Craft Printer" and "Trailside Country School," arranged alphabetically. The records in this series were originally in unordered folders, except for the two "Dissertation Research" folders, which were collected in one 3-ring binder. The original order of items and the folders titles (where they existed) have been retained.
Acquisition
Maggie Holtzberg; 2018.
Related Material
Holtzberg was a student of the Trailside Country School. Two interviews created by the students of the school comprise another collection: School interviews from Maine and Pennsylvania, 1975, collected by Diana Cohen and students of the Trailside Country School (AFC 1977/019).
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research; access to collection materials may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Bibliography
Holtzberg-Call, Maggie. The Lost World of the Craft Printer (Urbana and Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1992). http://lccn.loc.gov/90024004.
Cohen, Michael J., 1929-. Our classroom is wild America; trailside education in action-encounters with self, society, and nature in America's first ecology expedition school (Jericho, N.Y., Exposition Press, 1974). http://lccn.loc.gov/74076019.
Biographical Note
Dr. Maggie Holtzberg received her PhD in folklore and folklife from the University of Pennsylvania in 1987. Prior to that she gained a BA in ethnomusicology from Wesleyan University (1979). She was also a student of the traveling Trailside Country School from 1972-1973. She has written and published multiple books, including Keepers of Tradition: Art and Folk Heritage in Massachusetts (2008), The Lost World of the Craft Printer (1992), and Portrait of Spirit: One Story at a Time (1996). She has also produced and directed documentaries, recordings, and public events, including the film Gandy Dancers (1994) and the exhibition Keepers of Tradition: Art and Folk Heritage (2008). In addition to serving on and leading state, national, and regional art and folklore councils and agencies, Holtzberg has managed and directed folklife programs in both Massachusetts and Georgia.
Scope and Content
The Maggie Holtzberg collection documents, through interviews and photographs, the occupational folklife and craft of hot metal typesetters, compositors, and printers. Holtzberg interviewed skilled craftsmen and women who experienced the disruptive technology and transition in the printing industry from mechanical typesetting, "hot metal," to computer-aided photocomposition or "cold type." She interviewed retired printers residing at the Union Printers Home in Colorado Springs, Colorado and craft printers at Heritage Printers in Charlotte, North Carolina, among others. Interviews were conducted between 1983-1988. The collection includes the production files for Holtzberg's book, The Lost World of the Craft Printer (University of Illinois Press, 1992); correspondence with folklorists Archie Green and Judith McCulloh, and notes from meetings with Holtzberg's dissertation advisors at the University of Pennsylvania -- Henry Glassie, Ray Birdwhistle, and with Ken Goldstein, whom she interviewed about his experience in the printing industry. The collection also includes two journals written while Maggie Holtzberg was a student from 1972-1973 at the Trailside Country School, based in Killington, Vermont. The Trailside Country School was a traveling high school run by Michael Cohen and Diana Cohen that taught cultural documentation. The notebooks include diary entries, song lyrics, music transcription, and ephemera from locations throughout the United States where the students traveled. Photographs include the 46 illustrations for Holtzberg's book, 31 slides, plus snapshots from Holtzberg's fieldwork with printers and a few from the Trailside Country School. One of the interviews with printers was conducted by folklorist Jan Rosenberg.
Container List
- Series 1: Interviews, 1983-1992
  Interviews with craftsmen concerning their experiences in the printing industry, typically regarding the shift from "hot metal" mechanical typesetting to "cold-type" computer-aided photocomposition. Earlier interviews were conducted as part of Holtzberg's dissertation research, and those created after 1987 were conducted as part of her monograph The Lost World of the Craft Printer. Some interviews were not recorded. In those cases Holtzberg wrote notes and summaries. Some recorded interviews do not have full transcripts.
  - Interview summaries, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Notes from interviews conducted as part of dissertation, does not include notes for interviews conducted after 1986.
  - Greer Allen and Sue Allen interview, 1986 February 22
    - Sound recording on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR01)
    - Transcript (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Ernest Boyland interview, Little Rock, Arkansas, 1992 August 7
    Interviewed by Jan Rosenberg for the Texarkana Regional Arts and Humanities Council (TRAHC) Folklife Program. Interview was not created by Holtzberg as part of her research.
    - Sound recordings on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR02 - SR03)
    - Transcript (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Dan Burns interview, 1985 September 12
    - Sound recording on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR04)
    - Transcript (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Bob Culp interviews, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1985 June 21 - 1986 March 14
    - Sound recording on cassette, 1986 March 14 (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR05)
    - Transcript and interview notes, 1985 June 21 - 1986 March 14, manuscripts; 4 color photographic prints (Box-folder 1/5)
      Includes notes from interviews and interactions with Culp conducted between June 1985 and June 1987, in addition to a transcript for the recorded March 14th 1986 interview. Photographs are four portraits likely by Maggie Holtzberg.
  - Karen Gaines interviews, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1985 June 21 - 1986 March 14
    - Interview Notes (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Kenneth S. Goldstein interview, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1984 November 2
    - Sound recording on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR06)
    - Transcript (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Carl Gross interview, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1983 November 2 and 1986 February 17
    - Interview notes (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Dick Harrison interview, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1983 November 23
    - Sound recording on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR07)
    - Transcript (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Heritage Printers interviews, Charlotte, North Carolina, 1986 November 13-14 and 1986 December
    Recordings from a trip to Heritage Printers, which was a fully operating hot metal print shop in Charlotte, North Carolina. Includes interviews with Bob Earnhardt, Bill (Earl) Loftin, Rick Newell, and Earl Powell.
    - Sound recordings on cassette, 1986 November 13-14 (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR08 - SR10)
    - Transcript, 1986 December (Box-folder 1/10)
      Transcript is Holtzberg's first-person narrative recounting of her experience visiting Heritage Printers in Charlotte, North Carolina, and interviewing the employees.
    - Notes and research materials (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Ed Jacob and Dick Harrison interview, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1983 October 24
    - Interview notes (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Ed Jacob interview, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1983 November 30
    - Sound recording on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR11)
    - Transcript and interview notes (Box-folder 1/13)
  - "John C. Spencer Auction," Chester, Pennsylvania, 1988 February 1-3
    John Spencer Co. was a print shop that had been in business since 1864. When the company closed, Holtzberg attended the auction of its assets. Included are public notices of the auction, Holtzberg's notes, photographs, and recordings of the event, and one printing industry journal article reporting on the event.
    - Sound recordings on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR12 - SR 14)
    - Interview notes, manuscripts; 22 photographic prints (Box-folder 1/14)
      Includes materials promoting and documenting the auction and photos of the workshop and auction.
  - Samuel F. Kleinman interview, 1983 November 18
    - Interview notes (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Packard Press tour, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1984 October 31
    - Interview notes (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Bertram A. Powers interview, New York, New York, 1984 December 28 and 1985 November 1
    - Interview notes (Box-folder 1/17)
      Includes subject file about Mr. Powers, and one letter from him.
  - "Union Printers Home" interviews, Colorado Springs, Colorado, 1988 February 1-5
    Documentation and recordings of Holtzberg's trip to the Union Printers Home, from February 1st to 5th 1988. The Union Printers Home, founded in 1892, was a low cost retirement facility located in Colorado Springs, Colorado, for members of the International Typographical Union. Series includes notes, recordings, and photographs from Holtzbergs visit, and ephemera and research materials documenting the Home. Holtzberg's interview with Tony Donagy was not recorded, and materials for it are contained in the "Transcripts" and "Interview Notes and Research Materials" folders.
    - Transcripts (Box-folder 1/18)
      Transcripts for all the recordings in the series except the "Museum Tour." Also includes the transcript for Holtzberg's interview with Tony Donagy, which was not recorded.
    - Interview notes and research materials (Box-folder 1/19)
      Interview notes for all the recordings in the series. Also includes the notes for Holtzberg's interview with Tony Donagy, which was not recorded.
    - Photographs and slides, 10 photographic prints; 31 35mm slides (Box-folder 1/20)
    - Neil Fuller, 1988 February 1-2
      - Interview sound recording on cassette, 1988 February 1 (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR15)
      - "Museum Tour" sound recording on cassette, 1988 February 2 (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR16)
    - Jim Spurlock and Frank Koncel, 1988 February 2
      - Sound recordings on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR15 - SR16)
    - Joe Malady, 1988 February 3
      - Sound recording on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR17)
    - Amelia Story and Hazel Orff, 1988 February 3
      - Sound recording on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR18)
    - "Birthday Party," 1988 February 3
      Includes interviews with Phil Weinstein and Fred Zaner
      - Sound recording on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR19)
    - Filadelphio Valdez, 1988 February 5 - 1991 September 21
      - Sound recording on cassette, 1988 February 5 (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR19)
      - Correspondence, 1988 April 3 - 1991 September 21, manuscripts; 6 photographic prints (Box-folder 1/21)
    - Sandy Bevis, 1988 February 5
      - Sound recording on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR20)
    - Clifford Gallant, 1988 February 5
      - Sound recordings on cassette (Item id AFC 2018/013: SR20 - SR21)
  - Barnie Weeks interview, Montgomery, Alabama, 1988 December 12
    - Transcript (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Miscellaneous Short Interviews - Notes, 1986 January 31 - 1986 February 21 (Box-folder 1/23)
    Includes notes from Holtzberg's interviews and interactions with Rudy De Felice, Bill Glick, Richard Grasby, and John Peckham.
- Series 2: Manuscripts, correspondence, and production files, 1972-2002, Bulk: 1983-1994
  Series primarily contains records, manuscripts, and research materials created or collected by Holtzberg related to her study of "hot metal" typesetting during her PhD research in folklore and folklife and the publication of her manuscript "The Lost World of the Craft Printer." The major subseries is "The Lost World of the Craft Printer," which contains production files and correspondence with the University of Illinois Press concerning the editing and publication of that book. A unique subseries otherwise unrelated to the other records in the collection is Holtzberg's journals from her time as a high school student at the Trailside Country School in 1972-1973.
  - Dissertation research, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 2/1-2)
    Holtzberg's correspondence and notes from interactions with advisors, including Henry Glassie, Ray Birdwhistell, Dan Traister, and Alastair Reid. Also includes readings, her notes on methodology, and drafts of papers and articles.
  - Archie Green - correspondence, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 2/3-4)
    Includes some correspondence with others, including Alastair Reid and Judith McCulloh, and letters which Archie Green wrote to others on behalf of Holtzberg.
  - "The Lost World of the Craft Printer," 1986-2002
    Records concerning the contracting, editing, production, and release of Holtzberg's 1992 manuscript, The Lost World of the Craft Printer for the University of Illinois Press. The correspondence in the subseries includes some additional information about Holtzberg's research interview subjects.
    - Dust jacket, 1992 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Illustrations, line art, and photos, undated, 56 photographic prints; 3 4x5 black and white negatives; 4 35mm negative strips; 4 illustrations (Box-folder 2/6-7)
      Materials and layout mockups for a majority of the illustrations and photographs in The Lost World of the Craft Printer. Includes prints of some of the slides in the Union Printers Home photographs folder (box 1, folder 18).
      - Draft, "No More High Hats," 1990 March, 1 5.25" computer diskette; 16 computer files (Item id AFC 2018/013: C001)
        "No More High Hats" was the working title for the Lost World of the Craft Printer. The files are a pre-print draft of the book saved on a 5.25" floppy. They are wordperfect 5.1 formatted, and appear to have some data corruption. This floppy was originally housed in box two, folder six. The floppy has been reformatted to a digital disk image and the files are available in the Folklife Reading Room by request.
    - Judith McCulloh - University of Illinois Press - correspondence, 1986-2002, Bulk: 1986-1994 (Box-folder 2/8-9)
      Judith McCulloh was Holtzberg's Executive Editor for The Lost World of the Craft Printer. Correspondence concerns the contracting, editing, and production of the book.
    - Permissions - correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 2/10)
      Correspondence concerns the licensing of works for reproduction in The Lost World of the Craft Printer
    - Permissions - informants, 1990 (Box-folder 2/11)
      Includes correspondence securing permissions from informants and interviewees' for reuse of their statements. Includes some correspondence with interviewees and their families, and information on some interviewees' whereabouts in 1992.
    - Reviews, 1992-1996, manuscripts; 1 photographic print (Box-folder 3/1)
      Professional and personal reviews of the Lost World of the Craft Printer, including some correspondence with printers.
    - University of Illinois production, 1990-1992, manuscripts; 4 photographic prints (Box-folder 3/2)
      Correspondence concerns the editing, design, production, and promotion of The Lost World of the Craft Printer. Three of the photographs are historical pictures of the Union Printers Home.
  - New York Typographical Union No. 6 contract, 1984 March 31, 1 printed booklet (Box-folder 3/3)
  - "Old Times in the Print Shop" booklet, reproduction, 1939 (Box-folder 3/4)
    Photocopy reproduction of "Old Times in the Print Shop" booklet from 1939, produced by Sam'l Bingham's Son MFG. CO. in Chicago. The booklet features illustrations and descriptions of the lifestyles and culture of printers in the 1920s.
  - Printing research, 1984-1998, bulk: 1984-1987 (Box-folder 3/5)
    Newspaper clippings, ephemera, notes, and other materials concerning the history and culture of printers and the printing trade.
  - Responses to newsletter queries, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 3/6)
    Holtzberg placed adds reaching out to printing professionals in both the March/April 1986 issue of the American Printing History Association Newsletter and the April 1986 issue of "The Printer" serial. The folder includes a few brief responses to those requests, and copies of the serials.
  - Carl Schlesinger - correspondence, 1987-1990, manuscripts; 1 photographic print (Box-folder 3/7)
    Photograph is a still from Schlesinger's documentary film "Farewell, Etaoin Shrdlu."
  - Trailside Country School, 1972-1973
    Two journals written while Maggie Holtzberg was a student at the Trailside Country School, based in Killington, Vermont. The Trailside Country School was a traveling high school run by Michael Cohen and Diana Cohen that taught cultural documentation. The notebooks include diary entries, song lyrics, music transcription, and ephemera from locations throughout the United States where the students traveled.
    - Journal, 1972 September - 1973 March, 1 bound notebook (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Journal, 1973 March-August, 1 bound notebook (Box-folder 3/9)